A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, RG 5 Program Files, Subgroup Grant Files FA1795
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Journalism, 1986-2016; 9; 37.6 Cubic Feet 99 letter document boxes
  - Online News Association, 20030153, 2005 May 1-2006 May 1 (Box 96, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4143
    Online News Association, 20030153, $53,800. To create online training modules using the best work in digital journalism.
  - Radio and Television News Directors Foundation, 20030012, 2003 March 11-2006 October 31 (Box 96, Folder 2-4)
    Knight File Number - 4120
    Radio and Television News Directors Foundation, 20030012, $2,500,000. To improve electronic journalism in America's high schools.
  - Syracuse University, 20030021, 2003 March 11-2006 March 11 (Box 97, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4122
    Syracuse University, 20030021, $500,000. To expand news media use of TRACFED, a database that tracks the federal government.
  - The Conservation Company, (TCC), 20030008, 2003 March 11-2006 December 31 (Box 97, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4123
    The Conservation Company, (TCC), 20030008, $450,000. To teach journalism organizations how to raise money from their members.
  - University of California, Berkeley, 20030125, 2003 December 9-2006 July 31 (Box 98, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4125
    University of California, Berkeley, 20030125, $50,000. To coordinate a network of top journalism schools to produce innovative broadcast news.
  - The University of Maryland, 20030112, 2003 September 9-2006 September 9 (Box 98, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4126
    The University of Maryland, 20030112, $2.42 million. To expand the reach of the Knight Center for Specialized Journalism.
  - WNYC Radio, 20050061, 2005 May 1-2006 May 1 (Box 98, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4144
    WNYC Radio, 20050061, $150,000. To continue support for "On The Media," a public radio program reporting on the world of journalism.
  - The World Press Institute, 20030104, 2003 September 9-2006 September 9 (Box 98, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4127
    The World Press Institute, 20030104, $405,000. For fellowships that bring young international journalists to the United States.
  - American Press Institute, 20030136, 2003 September 9-2007 December 31 (Box 99, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4233
    American Press Institute, 20030136. $1 million to implement The Learning Newsroom concept nationally.
  - American Press Institute, 20030136 - The Learning Newsroom (Box 99, Folder 4)
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors Foundation, 20060092, 2006 September 1-2007 September 30 (Box 99, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4234
    American Society of Newspaper Editors Foundation, 20060092. $146,750 to expand National Sunshine Week in 2007 to help raise public awareness for open government issues.
  - Associated Press Managing Editors, 20030107, 2003 September 9-2007 September 9 (Box 100, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4235
    Associated Press Managing Editors, 20030107. $1 million for general operating support, and to create NewsTrain, a national network of regional journalism training sites.
  - Committee to Protect Journalists, 20050041, 2005 May 1-2007 May 1 (Box 101, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4238
    Committee to Protect Journalists, #20050041. $100,000 for general operating support.
  - George Washington University, 20060071, 2006 July 1-2007 July 1 (Box 101, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4240
    George Washington University, 20060071. $200,000 to develop a Prime Movers high school journalism program in Philadelphia.
  - Harvard University, 20050037, 2005 March 15-2007 July 31 (Box 102, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4220
    Harvard University, 20050037. $280,000 to support Nieman fellows from Latin America during the next two years.
  - Inter American Press Association Press Institute, 20050037, 2003 March 11-2007 March 11 (Box 102, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4221
    Inter American Press Association Press Institute, 20050037. $3.6 million (over four years) for operating support, and to expand the Impunity project to protect journalists and promote press freedom in the Americas.
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 9900190, 1999 September 13-2007 December 31 (Box 103, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4223
    Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 9900190. $2.2 million over 5 years for a partial challenge grant for an additional endowment to increase the number of stipends for Knight Science Journalism Fellows.
  - Radio and Television News Directors Foundation, 20060094, 2006 September 1-2007 September 30 (Box 105, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4226
    Radio and Television News Directors Foundation, 20060094. $250,000 to improve electronic journalism in America's high schools.
  - Syracuse University, 20060024, 2006 April 1-2007 May 31 (Box 105, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4228
    Syracuse University, 20060024. $160,000 to increase the impact of TRACFED, a database of government actions used nationally by news media.
  - TCC Group, 20050036, 2005 March 15-2007 March 15 (Box 105, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4227
    TCC Group, 20050036. $500,000 to expand the Challenge Fund for Journalism, a program that teaches groups how to build their own organizations.
  - University of Maryland, 20040176, 2004 September 14-2007 August 30 (Box 106, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4229
    University of Maryland, 20040176. $1 million to launch New Voices, a re-granting and education program designed to seed community news experiments.
  - University of Montana Foundation, 20040105, 2004 June 15-2007 June 15 (Box 106, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4230
    University of Montana Foundation, 20040105. $475,000 to expand "Reznet," an online student newspaper for Native Americans attending tribal colleges lacking student media.
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors Foundation, 20070179, 2007 November-2008 November 1 (Box 107, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4463
    20070179, American Society of Newspaper Editors Foundation, $160,000. To create a new First Amendment awareness campaign and strengthen national Sunshine Week in 2008.
  - Aspen Institute, 20060144, 2006 December 1-2008 December 1 (Box 107, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4462
    Aspen Institute, 20060144, $250,000. To help national media policy makers understand community media issues by holding roundtables and a conference.
  - George Washington University, 20070180, 2007 November 1-2008 July 30 (Box 109, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4476
    George Washington University, 20070180, $250,000. To complete a new approach to starting student media by establishing Media Clubs in Philadelphia.
  - Harvard University, 20050058, 2005 May 1-2008 July 31 (Box 110, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4481
    Harvard University, 20050058, $200,000. To support a task force of journalism school deans to research key news issues.
  - International Center for Journalists, 20070003, 2007 February 1-2008 February 1 (Box 110, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4483
    International Center for Journalists, 20070003, $250,000. To start a global business journalism program at Tsinghua University.
  - MinnPost, 20070131, 2007 October 1-2008 September 30 (Box 112, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4487
    MinnPost, 20070131, $250,000. To help launch a new kind of "digital daily," a quality nonprofit online news organization serving the state of Minnesota.
  - Philadelphia's Children First Fund, 20070112, 2007 August 1-2008 August 1 (Box 113, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4495
    Philadelphia's Children First Fund, 20070112, $125,000. To launch the first phase of merging Philadelphia's new Media Clubs into the regular ongoing operations of the school district.
  - Tides Center, 20070252, 2007 November 30-2008 December 31 (Box 114, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4500
    Tides Center, 20070252, $250,000. To pioneer a new way of covering political campaigns by going beyond the red-vs.-blue debate.
  - University of California, Berkeley, 20050032, 2005 March 15-2008 October 31 (Box 114, Folder 5, Box 115, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4503
    University of California, Berkeley, 20050032, $1.5 million. To coordinate experimental "News 21" projects at leading journalism schools, teaching top students to work in teams to cover a large, complex story. 2 folders (folder 2 is in box 115)
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors Foundation, 20060131, 2006 November 1-2009 March 31 (Box 115, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4690
    American Society of Newspaper Editors Foundation, 20060131, $250,000. To revitalize high school journalism and revamp www.highschooljournalism.org.
  - Committee to Protect Journalists, 20070167, 2007 October 1-2009 September 30 (Box 117, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4696
    Committee to Protect Journalists, 20070167, $550,000. To test Impunity Project experiments in Russia and the Philippines.
  - Northwestern University, 20030137, 2003 September 9-2009 January 31 (Box 119, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4712
    Northwestern University, 20030137, $1,967,500. To launch the Newsroom Training Initiative.
  - The University of Alabama, 20040180, 2004 September 14-2009 September 14 (Box 122, Folder 1-3)
    Knight File Number - 4715
    The University of Alabama, 20040180, $1,475,000. To establish a master's degree in community journalism, taught inside a working newspaper.
  - University of Missouri Systems, 20050193, 2005 September 20-2009 September 20 (Box 122, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4716
    University of Missouri Systems, 20050193, $1,700,000. To establish a new home for the National Freedom of Information Coalition and expand its ability to support state groups.
  - The University of Texas, 20020010, 2002 March 12-2009 March 31 (Box 123, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4717
    The University of Texas, 20020010, $2,000,000. To create the Knight Center for Journalism in the Americas.
  - World Wide Web Foundation, 20080097, 2008 August 1-2009 April 30 (Box 123, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4719
    World Wide Web Foundation, 20080097, $200,000. To support the creation and launch of the World Wide Web.
  - American Society of News Editors Foundation, 20070039, 2007 March 12-2010 March 31 (Box 123, Folder 4-5)
    Knight File Number - 4832
    American Society of News Editors Foundation, 20070039, $2,750,000 to teach the next generation of journalists, increase student media and improve First Amendment awareness among all high school students by expanding highschooljournalism.org.
  - The City University of New York, 20080039, 2008 March 17-2010 April 30 (Box 124, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4834
    The City University of New York, 20080039, $250,000 to extend a novel program helping journalism students get internships as part of a practical curriculum and to help establish CUNY's Graduate School of Journalism.
  - Committee to Protect Journalists, 20090158, 2009 November 4-2010 October 31 (Box 124, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4835
    Committee to Protect Journalists, 20090158, $250,000, to move Impunity Project pilots in Russia and the Philippines towards sustainability, and expand to an additional country.
  - International Center for Journalists, 20070166, 2007 September 16-2010 October 31 (Box 126, Folder 2-3)
    Knight File Number - 4841
    International Center for Journalists, 20070166, $3,815,000 to advance journalism excellence and free expression worldwide through a redesigned, high-impact, project-based Knight International Journalism Fellowship program.
  - National Public Radio, 20070163, 2007 September 16-2010 March 31 (Box 128, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4848
    National Public Radio, 20070163, $1,500,000, to help NPR move itself from a public radio company to a public media company.
  - Research Foundation of the City University of New York, 20090052, 2009 June 1-2010 June 30 (Box 129, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4854
    Research Foundation of the City University of New York, 20090052, $250,000, for the New Business Models for News Project, to openly produce detailed business plans that will be used to create sustainable models for the future of news.
  - The American University, 20080075, 2008 July 1-2011 November 30 (Box 130, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5002
    Grant 20080075, The American University, $2,400,000 to expand J-Lab's activities, while increasing institutional support for J-Lab by moving it to American University.
  - Aspen Institute, 20070275, 2007 December 10-2011 January 31 (Box 130, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5003
    Grant 20070275, Aspen Institute, $1,700,000 to call national attention to the issue by creating a high-level Knight Commission on the Information Needs of Communities in a Democracy.
  - Link Media, 20100088, 2010 July 1-2011 July 31 (Box 133, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5041
    Grant 20100088, Link Media, $245,000, to test a "semantic" news video player and related tols, with a focus on how young news consumers use the tool.
  - PBS Foundation, 20050187, 2005 September 20-2011 February 28 (Box 136, Folder 4-6)
    Knight File Number - 5030
    Grant 20050187, PBS Foundation, $3,000,000, to expand public affairs programming on public television with a new digital service called Public Square.
  - Radio & Television News Directors Foundation, 20070041, 2007 March 12-2011 May 31 (Box 137, Folder 1-2)
    Knight File Number - 5032
    Grant 20070041, Radio & Television News Directors Foundation, $1,200,000, to increase student broadcast media and improve First Amendment awareness among high school students.
  - Scoop Media, 20090036, 2009 April 1-2011 June 30 (Box 138, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5035
    Grant 20090036, Scoop Media, $242,800, to support the launch of Scoop44, a nonprofit youth-run news bureau covering the administration in Washington, DC.
  - Sunlight Foundation, 20090075, 2009 July 1-2011 August 31 (Box 138, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5036
    Grant 20090075, Sunlight Foundation, $565,000, to create and launch web tools allowing easily accessible public information on Congress.
  - Tides Center, 20090235, 2009 December 1-2011 December 31 (Box 138, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5037
    Grant 20090235, Tides Center, $200,000 to support developing both innovative business plans and innovative digital content delivery for investigative reporting through the hybrid model at Huffington Post Investigative Fund.
  - WNYC Radio, 20080026, 2008 March 10-2011 June 30 (Box 139, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5040
    Grant 20080026, WNYC Radio, $2,000,000, to support the launch of a new national morning show for public radio.
  - Minnesota Public Radio, 20080192, 2008 December 8-2012 December 8 (Box 144, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5164
    Grant 20080192, Minnesota Public Radio, $2,950,327, to expand Public Insight Journalism to an open-source platform and extend it beyond public radio and into Knight communities.
  - National Public Radio, 20090134, 2009 September 14-2012 December 31 (Box 145, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5166
    Grant 20090134, National Public Radio, $1,000,000, to extend Knight Foundation's digital training of the NPR newsroom by creating 12 local news test sites linked to one another and to NPR. This grant is the test project of the creation of a new local reporting network.
  - ProPublica, 20090073, 2009 June 8-2012 July 31 (Box 146, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5169
    Grant 20090073, Propublica, $1,010,000, to create a sustainable business model for ProPublica.
  - Salzburg Seminar American Studies, Inc., 20070278, 2007 December 10-2012 October 31 (Box 146, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5171
    Grant 20070278, Salzburg Seminar American Studies Inc., $1,220,000, to develop new global leadership programs to improve international news coverage, media development, journalism education and news literacy.
  - Stony Brook Foundation Inc., 20060110, 2006 September 12-2012 March 1 (Box 147, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5172
    Grant 20060110, Stony Brook Foundation Inc., $1,700,000, to establish the nation's first required college-wide program in News Literacy.
  - Tides Center, 20080033, 2008 March 17-2012 December 31 (Box 147, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5173
    Grant 20080033 Tides Center, $876,000, to create an economical way for poor people to use cell phones to create and gather information in forms difficult for authoritarian governments to control.
  - Tides Center, 20080033 - Freedom Fone It's for You: Final Report (Box 147, Folder 2)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 20070093, 2007 June 4-2012 July 31 (Box 149, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5176
    Grant 20070093, University of California, Berkeley, $2,800,000, to speed the news industry's digital transformation by increasing the number and impact of multimedia workshops offered by the Knight Digital Media Center.
  - Ashoka, 20070277, 2007 December 10-2013 August 1 (Box 150, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5328
    Grant 20070277, Ashoka, $3,000,000, to identify and invest in social entrepreneurs in journalism through Ashoka Fellowships.
  - Georgia College and State University Foundation, 20080190, 2008 December 8-2013 August 31` (Box 152, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5337
    Grant 20080190, Georgia College and State University Foundation, $1,500,000, to establish Milledgeville Community Connections: Digital Bridges, Bringing People Together, an initiative that will create the model for sustained, community-led adoption and use of broadband throughout Milledgeville and Baldwin County.
  - Poynter Institute for Media Studies, Inc., 20080078, 2008 July 1-2013 July 31 (Box 154, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5342
    Grant 2008007, Poynter Institute for Media Studies, Inc., $1,439,500, to extend Poynter's NewsU e-training into all newsrooms in the United States and focus new classes on digital training.
  - Sociedad Interamericana De Prensa, Inc., 20070165, 2007 October 1-2013 March 31 (Box 154, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5344
    Grant 20070165, Sociedad Interamericana De Prensa, Inc., $2,500,000, to broaden the impunity project to judges and lawmakers, making the unpunished killing of Latin American journalists "everybody's problems".
  - Tides Center, 20110279, 2011 August 1-2013 July 31 (Box 155, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5346
    Grant 20110279, Tides Center, $280,000, to expand ScraperWiki into a data community that helps journalists find, process, and share online data.
  - Tor Project, Inc., 20120168, 2012 July 1-2013 June 30 (Box 155, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5348
    Grant 20120168, The Tor Project, Inc., $320,000, to develop an open security toolkit for journalists, allowing them to avoid digital surveillance by governments and other groups.
  - University of Maryland College Park Foundation, 20060109, 2006 October 1-2013 November 30 (Box 155, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 5350
    Grant 20060109, University of Maryland College Park Foundation, $2,000,000, to complete a new college of journalism building, Knight Hall, to house the Knight Institute for the Future of Journalism.
  - Wiki Spot, 20100144, 2010 August 1-2013 February 28 (Box 156, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5352
    Grant 20100144, Wiki Spot, $360,500, to create an easy-to-use open source "wiki" platform tailored to the needs of local communities.
  - World Wide Web Foundation, 20080126, 2008 September 15-2013 October 31 (Box 156, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5353
    Grant 20080126, World Wide Web Foundation, $5,000,000, to be the first funder of the World Wide Web Foundation.
  - Committee to Protect Journalists, 2013-45290, 2013 April 1-2014 March 31 (Box 157, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5497
    Grant 2013-45290, Committee to Protect Journalists, $200,000, to fund innovative digital advocacy for press freedom.
  - Investigative News Network, 2013-45565, 2013 May 31-2014 May 31 (Box 157, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 5500
    Grant 2013-45565, Investigative News Network, $200,000, to provide business education and mentorship to online news publishers and assess the impact of the Community Journalism Executive Training (CJET) program.
  - National Public Radio, 20110357, 2011 December 12-2014 December 31 (Box 158, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 5506
    Grant 20110357, National Public Radio, $1,500,000, to expand digital training of public radio journalists.
  - Texas Tribune, 2013-43180, 2013 April 1-2014 October 31 (Box 159, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5508
    Grant 2013-43180, Texas Tribune, $1,500,000, to help solidify a successful sustainable business model at the Texas Tribune, and share best practices with other non-profit news organizations.
  - Cafedirect Producers Foundation, 20120405, 2013 June 1-2014 July 31 (Box 160, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5652
    Grant 20120405, Cafedirect Producers Foundation, $260,000, to refine and scale WeFarm, a mobile platform allowing smallholder farmers to ask questions, have them translated, and get answers back, through simple phones and SMS.
  - Detroit Educational Television Foundation, 2013-47739, 2013 December 1-2015 January 31 (Box 161, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5659
    Grant 2013-47739, Detroit Educational Television Foundation, $25,000, for Detroit Public Television to join the Detroit Journalism Cooperative, developing and sharing stories aimed at helping find solutions to the city's fiscal crisis.
  - GitMachines, 2014-48824, 2014 May 1-November 30 (Box 161, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 5663
    Grant 2014-48824, GitMachines, $186,901, to develop GovReady, an open source toolkit to certify software and IT systems for use by governments, so that governments can more easily work with open data and civic innovation projects.
  - New Michigan Media Detroit Journalism Cooperative, 2013-47746, 2013 December 1-2015 January 31 (Box 162, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5673
    Grant 2013-47746, New Michigan Media Detroit Journalism Cooperative, $30,000 for New Michigan Media to join the Detroit Journalism Cooperative, developing and sharing stories aimed at helping find solutions to the city's fiscal crisis.
  - New York Public Library, 2014-49388, 2014 July 1-2015 October 31 (Box 162, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 5675
    Grant 2014-49388, New York Public Library, $500,000 to support the New York Public Library's public hotspot program, which provides low-income families free internet access along with education and training initiatives.
  - Out of Eden Walk, 2013-42869, 2013 February 1-2015 February 1 (Box 163, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5677
    Grant 2013-42869, Out of Eden Walk, $200,000, to support experimentation with new long-form storytelling tools and approaches during Paul Salopek's 7-year journalistic walk around the world.
  - Rutgers University Foundation, 2014-49212, 2014 August 1-2015 August 30 (Box 163, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5683
    Grant 2014-49212, Rutgers University Foundation, $250,000, to support journalism excellence through diversity by contributing to the Gloria Steinem Endowed Chair in Media, Culture and Feminist Studies to examine and advance women's participation in media, especially at the decision-making levels.
  - Sexual Health Innovations, 2013-47594, 2013 December 31-2014 June 30 (Box 164, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5684
    Grant 2013-47594, Sexual Health Innovations, $35,000, to build an API for Private Results, an STD test result delivery service.
  - Trustees of Columbia University in the City of New York, 2014-48965, 2014 May 1-2015 May 30 (Box 164, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5686